Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco and my
name is Catherine and today
we have a great lesson
for you about traveling.
That's right. You know,
we have taken a look at
previous lessons where
you can buy a ticket,
how to book a flight,
what to do at the airport,
but now we are going
to see what we can do if
our flight gets canceled.
Okay, this is not a fun
situation but hopefully
with our help you'll be able
to understand what these
messages are about flights
that are canceled or delayed.
So let's take a listen to today's dialogue.
Good afternoon, sir. May I please see
your passport and reservation? Here you go.
Oh, I'm sorry, sir. This flight has been
canceled due to some mechanical problems.
Canceled? What am I
supposed to do now?
We apologize for any inconveniences
that may be caused by this.
If your flight is urgent,
I could put you on a
waiting list for another
flight this evening,
but it's on a first
come, first serve basis.
So there's no guarantee
you'll be able to take that flight.
What are my other options?
Well, if you can wait until tomorrow,
we will put you up in a
hotel for today and you
can take the scheduled
flight for tomorrow morning.
That's fine. I'll do that
then. Thank you for your
understanding, sir. I'll
book your flight now.
All right, we're back. So now it's time
for us to go into language takeaway.
Language takeaway. All
right, in language takeaway
today, we have about
four words or phrases.
The first one is the
reason for this cancellation.
The reason is
mechanical problems.
That's right. She
said that the airplane
has some mechanical
problems, and that's why
the flight is canceled. So
the key here is mechanical,
mechanical meaning like
related to machines, right?
All right, so something
that's a mechanical
problem has to do with the
actual structure of the plane.
That's right. So for example, maybe
something is wrong with the wings or maybe
something is wrong
with the engines.
Some type of problem that has to
do with the mechanics of the machine.
Right. And obviously,
if you have a
problem with the wings
or the wheels or the engine,
you don't want
to fly that plane.
That's right. So this
caused the canceled flight.
Now, after that, we heard
this word, we apologize for
any inconveniences. What's
an inconvenience, Marco?
That's right. Well,
obviously, I planned to
take this flight, let's
say Tuesday at 8 a.m.
And if the flight is
canceled, that means I have
to wait an hour or three
hours or maybe for the next day.
So it's an inconvenience.
It means it's
not convenient for me. It
causes me some trouble.
All right. So something
that is inconvenient
causes problems or
causes trouble. That's right.
For example, you have this
late flight or canceled flight.
That's an inconvenience.
But also, small things can
be inconvenient as well.
Like, I want to go home
at five. Unfortunately,
I have to write this report.
It's very inconvenient.
That's right. So maybe
you have a doctor's
appointment tomorrow
at 12, but you also have a
meeting at your work. So it's
inconvenient these two dates.
All right. They cause
problems for each other.
So under that, the
service person says if your
flight is urgent, I can
put you on a waiting list.
Right. Waiting list. So
this is another important
phrase to understand
when we're talking about
canceled flights. That's right. We
usually get put on a waiting list.
And it's basically a list with everyone's
names where you are waiting for
the next available
flight or you're waiting
for to be able to have
the service provided.
All right. So you can
have a waiting list at an
airport like here, but you
can also have a waiting
list at a restaurant,
right? That's right.
And some restaurants are
super popular and you got to
get on a waiting list.
So can I put my name on
the waiting list? That
means can you call me when
there's a free
table? Right. Exactly.
So even though we are on
this waiting list, it doesn't mean
that we are guaranteed
to be able to take this
flight this evening. So
there is no guarantee.
All right. This guarantee,
this is an important
thing to talk about because
a guarantee is something
that means that we will
definitely get a later flight.
Yeah, we promise. We promise.
So you often see the word
guarantee in advertisements.
For example, this TV has
a six-month guarantee.
So we guarantee it won't
break. If it does, we will fix it.
That's right. But no guarantee means
that we can't promise. We don't promise.
That's right. So it's possible
that you won't get a flight.
So for example, if you buy
a new car, the manufacturer
will guarantee that
it's in good condition
and it won't break down. But if you buy a
used car, it's unlikely that they will give
you that same
guarantee. No, that's right.
They cannot promise it
because they don't know.
Exactly. All right. So a lot
of words and phrases there.
Why don't we go
back and listen to our
dialogue again.
Good afternoon, sir.
May I please see your passport
and reservation? Here you go.
Oh, I'm sorry, sir. This flight has been
canceled due to some mechanical problems.
Canceled. What am I
supposed to do now?
We apologize for any inconveniences
that may be caused by this.
If your flight is
urgent, I could put you
on a waiting list for
another flight this evening,
but it's on a first-come,
first-serve basis.
So there's no guarantee
you'll be able to take that flight.
What are my other
options? Well, if you can wait
until tomorrow, we
will put you up in a hotel
for today and you can
take the scheduled flight for
tomorrow morning.
That's fine. I'll do that then.
Thank you for your understanding, sir.
I'll book your flight now.
All right. So now let's
take a look at three key
phrases that we have
prepared for you on fluency
builder. Fluency Builder. Okay.
So the first phrase we have
here is a very important one.
This tells us about the
cause of the problem.
The service person
said, "I'm sorry, sir.
This flight has been canceled
due to some mechanical problems.
" Right. So this
phrase due to, basically,
is saying because
of, right? That's right.
So this flight has been
canceled because of mechanical
problems. And remember,
this due is D-U-E.
That's right. D-U-E. So I think
it's kind of a nicer or more
formal way of saying because
of or the reason is exactly.
For example, the
picnic has been canceled
due to bad weather.
So it sounds a lot more
professional, a lot more
formal than if you say
because of bad weather.
All right. So just remember
here due to indicates
the cause or the reason.
It's like saying
because. All right.
Now when we were talking about
the flights, we said that we are
on the waiting list, but
in order to catch this
flight, they are going
to take people on a first
come first served basis. All
right. First come first served.
Now this is, this is again
a very common phrase.
It's related to that
waiting list thing
we're talking about. If
you have a waiting list,
usually the waiting list
is first come first served.
So I could say, um, you
know, am I guaranteed a spot?
And you could say, well,
it's first come for served.
Maybe, maybe not. Right. If I'm number
one on list, I will probably get a seat.
But if I'm number 30, probably
probably not. So what we mean
by it is that we don't
give priority to anyone.
We don't say, oh, you are
more important or you're
not whoever comes
first gets it. All right.
So if I come to the
restaurant at five o'clock,
I get to see it sit first.
But if you come at
five 10 year next
and after you five 30.
So it's first come first serve. It
depends on when you arrive.
That's right. So obviously
this wasn't convenient for us.
So we are going to
wait until tomorrow.
But the airline will
put us up in a hotel.
We will put you up in a
hotel. All right. So let's take this
as a phrase because we
all know what a hotel is.
It's a place where you
stay when you're on
holiday or business. But
to put someone up, uh,
what exactly does this
mean? Basically, you are
paying for that person to
stay at that hotel and you
made the reservation and
you're going to pay for the room.
So I will put you
up means I will pay
for your room at a hotel.
Right. And it's usually
only for accommodation
for a hotel. Right.
You can say, I will
put you up for a meal.
No, but you can say, I'll put
you up at my house, which
means I will let you stay
the night at my house.
So not food, but actually
sleeping done. Right.
So it usually involves
sleeping. That's right.
So for example, you could
say, um, he's coming to
our hometown for the wedding.
I will put him up at my house.
Right. Or if your
company sent you to
Japan, you say, my company
put me up at the high hotel.
Ooh, fancy. Nice.
All right. So that's all
the phrases we have for you.
Let's listen to our dialogue one last time.
Good afternoon, sir. May
I please see your passport
and reservation. Here
you go. Oh, I'm sorry, sir.
This flight has been canceled
due to some mechanical
problems canceled. What
am I supposed to do now?
We apologize for any inconveniences
that may be caused by this.
If your flight is urgent, I could put you
on a waiting list for another flight this
evening, but it's on the
first come first serve basis.
So there's no guarantee
you'll be able to
take that flight. What
are my other options?
Well, if you can wait
until tomorrow, we will
put you up in a hotel for
today and you can take
the scheduled flight
for tomorrow morning.
That's fine. I'll do that
then. Thank you for your
understanding, sir. I'll
book your flight now.
All right. We're back.
So we're talking about
canceled flights. Usually
it's due to bad weather
and usually you can
catch another flight soon,
but sometimes you do have these problems
like when there was the whole 9/11 thing.
I think a lot of flights were
canceled or the volcano that
erupted and European flights
were grounded for a long time.
Yes, that's right.
So sometimes there
are natural disasters.
Sometimes there are man-made
disasters, but you actually
said a very interesting
word there and something
that I think people who
are learning about this
should definitely study.
The word is grounded. A
flight has been grounded.
Yes, that means that the
airplane will stay on the ground.
It means the plane will not fly.
Okay, so when planes are
grounded because of bad
weather or because
of a natural disaster like
a volcano, it's a very
serious situation because
the people who are
going to fly can't know.
Now in our dialogue,
we saw that they handled
it. The airline handled it very, very
well, but I think this is a very rare case.
You've had flights canceled
before. How did they handle it?
I have. I've had two or
three flights canceled one
time because of a blizzard,
so all flights were grounded.
The weather was very
bad, very dangerous.
The airline company
said, "Well, we're sorry,
there are no more flights,
but if you come back
tomorrow, we can help
you." I was very lucky because
they did not give me a
hotel. They did not put me
up in a hotel, but I was
staying with a friend,
so my friends put me up
at her house. But the other
time, the flight was
canceled. The airline put
me on a flight from
another company, another
airline company, and so
sometimes they can do that,
where they have a relationship with
another airline company, they can do that.
So usually they do try
to handle it relatively
well, but they've heard
sometimes that they are
not very understanding or very sympathetic
to the inconvenience they cause.
Definitely, and I think the worst is when
it's bad weather because everyone's angry,
and all the customers
need to go somewhere,
but they can't because
there are no flights.
And so the people who are working for
the airlines get very frustrated or upset.
Right, because basically
it's not their fault.
It's not their fault.
There's bad weather,
so there's not really much
compensation the company can give you.
No, definitely not. Not
really their fault, but
it's hard not to get
frustrated because you want
to go home, you're tired,
you don't want to pay
for another nine a hotel, so
I can understand both signs.
Right. Well, it's an
interesting topic, and
I'm sure many of our
listeners who have traveled,
have had a flight delayed
or canceled, so you can
come to our website and
share your story with us,
and of course, if you have
any questions or comments.
You can find us
at EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you all there.
All right. Bye, guys.